MathPath ────────────────────────────────── Deterministic Multilingual EdTech Platform Complete Product &amp; Technical Specification Mathematics &amp; Physics • 9 Languages • No AI • Mastery-Based PART A: Product Requirements | PART B: Technical Specification PART A — PRODUCT REQUIREMENTS DOCUMENT (PRD) A1 — PRODUCT VISION &amp; STRATEGIC GOALS MathPath is a self-guided, deterministic, multilingual mathematics and physics learning platform. It contains NO artificial intelligence, NO machine learning, and NO human educator roles. All learning paths, assessments, and feedback are governed entirely by strict, rule-based logic. 📌 Core promise: Any student in any of 9 supported languages, on any device, with or without internet, can progress from foundational to mastery-level mathematics through a rigorously sequenced, bias-free, deterministic system. Strategic Goals Goal Description Mastery gating Students advance only by demonstrating genuine understanding — never by time spent Zero AI dependency All logic is deterministic and auditable — no black-box behaviour Deep localization 9 languages with culturally correct number formatting, not just translated text Offline-first Full learning capability in low-connectivity environments Math anxiety reduction Design every interaction to build confidence, not punish failure Target Audience Segment Description Primary Language School students (Gr 8–12) Building foundational to advanced math Tamil, Hindi, English Undergraduate STEM Physics formulas, calculus, linear algebra English, Japanese, Korean Self-learners Curiosity-driven adult learners All 9 languages Rural / low-bandwidth users Need offline, lightweight, affordable access Tamil, Hindi, Marathi, Telugu A2 — MONETIZATION MODEL ⚠ Monetization model affects DB schema, RBAC roles, and content gating logic. Define this before any technical implementation. Tier Structure Feature FREE PRO — $4/mo or $34/yr INSTITUTIONAL Languages English + 1 regional All 9 languages All 9 + custom Difficulty levels Levels 1–2 only All 4 levels All 4 levels Offline download Limited (5 modules) Unlimited Unlimited Certificates None Per topic on mastery Branded certificates Leaderboard Global weekly only Global + friends scope Class leaderboard Admin dashboard None Personal stats Full institutional dash GeoGebra interactive View only Full interactive Full interactive Audio narrations None All supported langs All supported langs Pricing Psychology $34/year = $2.83/month — position as &apos;cheaper than one tutoring hour&apos; Show annual savings clearly: ~~$48/year~~ → $34 (save $14) 14-day free trial of Pro — no credit card required Institutional pricing: per-seat annual license, volume discounts at 50/200/500 seats Free tier is genuinely useful — not crippled — to drive word-of-mouth in target markets Revenue Sharing for Localization (Phase 2) Regional language contributors (e.g., Tamil educators) receive revenue share for validated translations This funds content quality while reducing internal translation cost A3 — LANGUAGE &amp; LOCALIZATION STRATEGY Phased Language Launch Phase Languages Timeline Phase 1 — Launch English, Tamil, Hindi Launch Phase 2 — Regional Marathi, Kannada, Telugu, Malayalam Month 4 Phase 3 — International Japanese, Korean Month 8 📌 Formulas (LaTeX) are NEVER translated — they are mathematically universal. Only labels, instructions, explanations, and UI text are localized. Localization Scope per Language Content Type Localization Rule UI text / navigation Fully translated in all 9 languages Mathematical formulas (LaTeX) Language-invariant — NEVER translated GeoGebra diagram labels Translated, math logic identical across all languages Worked example text Fully translated Audio narrations Required for English, Tamil, Hindi at Phase 1 launch Number formatting Locale-aware via Intl.NumberFormat — see below Right-to-left scripts Not required for any of the 9 languages (all LTR) Number Formatting Rules Use JavaScript Intl.NumberFormat — never hardcode number display Indian locales (Tamil, Hindi, Marathi, Kannada, Telugu, Malayalam): apply Indian grouping — three rightmost digits grouped, then pairs (e.g., 12,34,567.89) Japanese / Korean: standard grouping with region-appropriate symbols English: standard Western grouping (1,234,567.89) Currency symbol placement: locale-determined, never hardcoded Decimal separator: period for English/Japanese/Korean, period also standard for Indian locales (confirm per sub-locale) UI Container Responsiveness for Script Length Tamil and Malayalam scripts are significantly longer than English equivalents — containers must expand dynamically Japanese and Korean are more compact — do not leave excessive whitespace Never use fixed-width text containers alongside GeoGebra diagrams — use flex/grid with min/max constraints Run automated text overflow tests for all 9 languages on every UI update A4 — PEDAGOGICAL FRAMEWORK &amp; CONTENT STRUCTURE 📌 All pedagogy is based on Cognitive Load Theory (CLT). Every design decision must reduce extraneous load, manage intrinsic load, and maximize germane load. Four-Level Difficulty Progression Level Name Description 1 Concrete &amp; Visual GeoGebra-led exploration with real-world context. No independent problem-solving. Fully worked examples only. 2 Procedural (Fading Guidance) Connect visuals to MathJax formulas. Introduce early active recall. Partial worked examples with student completion. 3 Abstract Application Remove visual aids. Require independent multi-step problem solving. Worked examples fully faded. 4 Complex Derivations Mastery level for non-standard heuristics — Diophantine equations, advanced physics derivations, proof construction. Expertise Reversal Trigger (Hardcoded Rule) 📌 When a user scores &gt;80% on practice questions within a module, automatically fade out worked examples and require independent problem-solving. This is a deterministic system rule — no exceptions. Score &lt; 60%: serve fully solved worked examples before every practice question Score 60–80%: serve partially completed worked examples (student fills final steps) Score &gt; 80%: remove all worked examples — independent solving only On module retry (after lockout): reset to full worked examples regardless of prior score Content Module Schema ⚠ Every module must conform to this schema. Developers must not invent ad-hoc content structures. { &quot;module_id&quot;: &quot;calc-derivatives-01&quot;, &quot;topic&quot;: &quot;Calculus&quot;, &quot;subtopic&quot;: &quot;Derivatives from First Principles&quot;, &quot;difficulty_level&quot;: 2, &quot;prerequisites&quot;: [&quot;calc-limits-03&quot;, &quot;alg-functions-02&quot;], &quot;content_blocks&quot;: [ { &quot;type&quot;: &quot;text | formula | diagram | audio&quot;, &quot;translations&quot;: { &quot;en&quot;: &quot;...&quot;, &quot;ta&quot;: &quot;...&quot;, &quot;hi&quot;: &quot;...&quot; }, &quot;formula_latex&quot;: &quot;\\lim_{h \\to 0} \\frac{f(x+h)-f(x)}{h}&quot;, &quot;geogebra_id&quot;: &quot;xyz123&quot; } ], &quot;worked_examples&quot;: [ { &quot;problem&quot;: &quot;...&quot;, &quot;steps&quot;: [&quot;step1&quot;, &quot;step2&quot;], &quot;solution&quot;: &quot;...&quot; } ], &quot;practice_questions&quot;: [ { &quot;question_id&quot;: &quot;q001&quot;, &quot;question_latex&quot;: &quot;...&quot;, &quot;answer&quot;: &quot;...&quot;, &quot;hint&quot;: &quot;...&quot;, &quot;explanation&quot;: &quot;...&quot;, &quot;recall_formula_id&quot;: &quot;euler-fermat-01&quot; } ], &quot;recall_formulas&quot;: [ { &quot;formula_id&quot;: &quot;euler-fermat-01&quot;, &quot;latex&quot;: &quot;...&quot;, &quot;recall_cue&quot;: &quot;...&quot; } ], &quot;min_questions_in_bank&quot;: 30 } CLT Design Rules (Non-Negotiable) Effect Rule Split Attention Effect ELIMINATE: Integrate explanatory text physically within diagrams — never separate panels Redundancy Effect ELIMINATE: Never present identical information simultaneously in two formats Modality Effect APPLY: Pair visual diagrams with localized audio narration, not on-screen text Worked Example Effect APPLY: Serve fully solved examples to novices — reduces cognitive load by 40%+ Expertise Reversal Effect APPLY: Remove worked examples above 80% threshold — they become a hindrance for experts A5 — LEARNING PATH &amp; PROGRESSION LOGIC 📌 All progression is mastery-based. No time-based unlocks. No skipping. These rules are enforced at the API level — not just in the UI. Prerequisite Enforcement Rules Rule Implementation Module unlock condition ALL prerequisite modules must score &gt;= 70% before a module is accessible Score to unlock next module Current module must score &gt;= 70% Score for Pro features (certificates) &gt;= 80% across all modules in a topic Failed module (&lt; 60%) Serve 2 additional worked examples, then retest with fresh randomized question set Failed module (3 consecutive fails) 24-hour lockout — prevents cramming, encourages rest Skip ahead Disabled at API level — UI cannot override this Score policy Last valid attempt (not best attempt) — prevents gaming via repeated tries Learning Path Graph (Sample Prerequisite Structure) Number Theory → Algebra Foundations → Functions &amp; Graphs → Trigonometry → Pre-Calculus Pre-Calculus → Differential Calculus → Integral Calculus → Multivariable Calculus Algebra Foundations → Linear Algebra → Matrices → Eigenvalues Trigonometry → Complex Numbers → Fourier Series Algebra Foundations → Statistics &amp; Probability → Distributions → Hypothesis Testing Mechanics → Thermodynamics → Electromagnetism → Quantum Foundations Assessment Integrity Rules Rule Specification Question bank minimum 30 questions per module — prevents question memorization Randomization Questions randomized per session — never same order twice Retry cooldown 24-hour lockout after 3 consecutive failures on same module Anti-cheat No copy-paste in active recall mode — disable right-click, Ctrl+C Browser back button Disabled during active recall session — navigate away = session ends Score authority Server is authoritative — client score submissions validated server-side Concurrent session Only one active assessment session allowed per user at a time A6 — GAMIFICATION &amp; RETENTION SYSTEM 📌 Gamification must reduce math anxiety, not amplify it. Every reward is objective, transparent, and deterministic. Points &amp; Rewards Action Points Awarded Complete a module (first attempt, score &gt;= 80%) 100 points Complete a module (score 70–79%) 70 points Correct active recall on first try 10 points per question Daily login streak maintained 5 points per day Topic mastery (all modules &gt;= 80%) 500 points + mastery badge Streak milestone (7 / 30 / 100 days) Bonus 50 / 200 / 1000 points Retention Loop Daily streak: any module activity = streak maintained Streak loss warning: push notification at 22:00 if no activity that day (opt-in) Points decay: 5% weekly decay on accounts with zero activity for 14+ days — creates urgency without punishing consistent users Weekly leaderboard: resets every Sunday midnight — prevents permanent top-10 lock-out by early adopters Leaderboard scope options: Global Weekly / Friends / Topic-specific (prevents demotivation from impossible gaps) Badges &amp; Certificates Achievement Requirement Module badge Score &gt;= 80% on module — awarded immediately Topic mastery badge All modules in topic &gt;= 80% Speed badge Complete module correctly within top 10% of time for that module Streak badges 7 / 30 / 100 day streaks Mastery certificate (Pro) All modules in a topic &gt;= 80% — downloadable, shareable image card Perfect recall badge 10 consecutive active recall questions correct in one session ✅ Badges and certificates are shareable as image cards — this is a key organic distribution mechanic. A7 — UX DESIGN PRINCIPLES Core Philosophy: Functional Minimalism Maximize whitespace — never crowd mathematical content Centralized design system — absolute micro-consistency across all components and all 9 languages Dark mode default for night study — critical for student user base Progress visualization always visible — students need to see how far they&apos;ve come Math Anxiety Reduction Rules Rule Implementation No &apos;fail&apos; state Replace FAIL with &apos;Not yet — here is the concept again&apos; Instant feedback Automated validation the moment an answer is submitted — never wait Actionable error messages Never just &apos;Wrong&apos;. Always: what went wrong + what to review Progress always visible Show: X modules completed, Y to go — never just a percentage Encouragement on streak loss Do not punish — &apos;Welcome back. Let&apos;s pick up where you left off.&apos; Worked examples on demand Students can always view a worked example before attempting (below 80% threshold) Accessibility (WCAG 2.1+ AA Compliance) Full keyboard navigation — no mouse required for any interaction Screen reader support: MathJax accessibility extensions for all equations (MathML output) High-contrast mode toggle — especially important for low-quality screens in target markets Audio narrations for all worked examples (Phase 1: English, Tamil, Hindi) Font size controls — minimum base size 16px, user-adjustable Focus indicators visible and high-contrast on all interactive elements All GeoGebra diagrams have text descriptions for screen readers Color is never the ONLY indicator of state — always pair with text or icon A8 — ADMIN DASHBOARD &amp; CONTENT OPERATIONS ⚠ &apos;System Administrator&apos; in RBAC must have clearly defined capabilities. Vague admin roles lead to security and content quality failures. Admin Dashboard Capabilities Area Capabilities Content management Add / edit / publish / unpublish modules per language. Assign difficulty, prerequisites, and topic tags. Translation workflow Upload translations per language, mark as reviewed, publish independently per locale User management View user progress, reset passwords, issue bans, escalate to institutional admin Analytics Completion rates per module, average attempts to pass, drop-off points, question difficulty heatmap Leaderboard moderation Remove fraudulent or anomalous scores with audit log Question bank Add, edit, retire questions. View per-question accuracy rates. Flag questions with &lt;20% pass rate for review. System health Cache hit rate, WebSocket connection count, offline sync queue size, error rates Institutional accounts Create, configure, and deactivate institutional licenses. View seat usage. Content Review Pipeline Draft: educator writes module content in English Technical review: second mathematician verifies derivation accuracy Pedagogy review: CLT compliance check — split attention, redundancy, modality effects LaTeX audit: notation consistency against style guide enforced Translation: regional language translators handle all non-formula text Translation QA: native-speaker review for each locale Accessibility check: MathML output verified, audio narration recorded Publish: module goes live, added to prerequisite graph PART B — TECHNICAL SPECIFICATION DOCUMENT (TSD) B1 — SYSTEM ARCHITECTURE OVERVIEW MathPath uses a hybrid architecture separating concerns cleanly: deterministic business logic (Django), real-time features (Node.js), optimized data fetching (GraphQL), and offline-capable PWA frontend (Next.js). Architecture Diagram (Component Map) Layer Technology &amp; Responsibility Frontend PWA React + Next.js — SSR, code splitting, SEO, offline shell via Service Worker Business Logic API Python + Django — RBAC, mastery rules, scoring, prerequisite enforcement, ACID transactions Real-time Service Node.js + WebSockets — live leaderboard updates, streak notifications Data Fetching Layer GraphQL — minimize data transfer, typed API for mobile clients Primary Database PostgreSQL — users, scores, enrollments, gamification ledger (ACID) Content Database MongoDB — multilingual content blocks, module JSON, translations Cache / Session Redis — session management, cached derivations, leaderboard state Math Rendering MathJax v3+ — server pre-rendered to MathML/SVG for offline + accessibility Interactive Diagrams GeoGebra — embedded, lazy-loaded, pre-downloaded for offline File Storage S3-compatible (Cloudflare R2) — audio narrations, certificate images, cached PDFs B2 — TECHNOLOGY STACK (DETAILED) Frontend Technology Purpose &amp; Notes React 18 + Next.js 14 (App Router) SSR for SEO, automatic code splitting, API routes, ISR for content pages TypeScript Type safety across entire codebase — mandatory TailwindCSS Dark mode default. Dynamic container sizing for multilingual text. MathJax v3 (or v4) Equation rendering. Pre-render server-side to MathML. Enable accessibility extensions. GeoGebra Embed API Interactive diagrams. Lazy-loaded. Pre-cached for offline. Labels localized. Framer Motion Step reveal animations, difficulty transition effects. Reduced-motion mode required. i18next Internationalization framework. Externalize all UI strings from day 1. Intl.NumberFormat All number display. Never hardcode numeric formatting. Locale-aware always. Workbox (Service Worker) PWA offline caching. Cache strategy defined per content type — see offline spec. Backend Technology Purpose &amp; Notes Python 3.11+ + Django 5 Business logic, RBAC, scoring rules, prerequisite enforcement. SQL injection / XSS protection built-in. Django REST Framework REST endpoints consumed by GraphQL resolver and internal services Node.js 20 + Socket.io Real-time WebSocket service for leaderboard updates and streak notifications GraphQL (Strawberry or Graphene) API layer — typed schema, minimize over-fetching on mobile connections Celery + Redis Async task queue — daily digest emails, streak decay calculations, certificate generation PostgreSQL 16 Primary ACID database — users, scores, enrollments, subscriptions, gamification ledger MongoDB 7 Content database — module JSON with multilingual translation arrays Redis 7 Session store, leaderboard cache, Celery broker, question bank cache Infrastructure &amp; DevOps Service Purpose Vercel Next.js frontend hosting — edge network for global latency Railway or Render Django + Node.js backend hosting Cloudflare R2 Audio narrations, certificate images, cached GeoGebra snapshots Cloudflare CDN MathJax assets, KaTeX fonts, static content Supabase or AWS RDS Managed PostgreSQL with daily snapshots MongoDB Atlas Managed MongoDB — multi-region for content availability GitHub Actions CI/CD pipeline — type check, test, lint, deploy to staging then prod Sentry Error monitoring on all services PostHog Product analytics — self-hostable, privacy-compliant for India/EU B3 — DATABASE SCHEMA (PostgreSQL) Core Tables users { id, email, name, avatar, tier, role, lang_pref, created_at, last_active } subscriptions { id, user_id, stripe_id, plan, status, expires_at } institutional_accs { id, name, admin_user_id, seats_total, seats_used, license_expires } topic_enrollments { id, user_id, topic_id, enrolled_at, status } module_progress { id, user_id, module_id, attempts, last_score, best_score, status, unlocked_at, completed_at } assessment_sessions { id, user_id, module_id, started_at, submitted_at, score, questions_json, answers_json, valid } gamification_ledger { id, user_id, event_type, points_delta, balance, ref_id, created_at } streaks { id, user_id, current_streak, longest_streak, last_activity_date } badges { id, user_id, badge_type, ref_id, awarded_at } leaderboard_weekly { id, user_id, week_start, points, rank } daily_active_recall { id, user_id, scheduled_formulas[], completed, due_date } MongoDB Collection: modules Stores all multilingual content. One document per module. Referenced by module_id across PostgreSQL. { module_id, topic, subtopic, difficulty_level, prerequisites: [module_ids], content_blocks: [{ type, translations: {en, ta, hi, ...}, formula_latex, geogebra_id }], worked_examples: [{ problem, steps[], solution, translations }], practice_questions: [{ question_id, question_latex, answer, hint, explanation, recall_formula_id }], recall_formulas: [{ formula_id, latex, recall_cue }], min_questions_in_bank: 30, version: 3, last_updated } B4 — AUTHENTICATION &amp; RBAC Roles Role Access Scope Notes Guest Browse public topic list only No progress saved. Prompt to register after 2 interactions. Learner (Free) Free tier content, global leaderboard Default role on registration Learner (Pro) All content, certificates, offline unlimited Requires active subscription Institutional Learner Institutional content + class leaderboard Assigned by institutional admin Institutional Admin Class dashboard, student progress, reports Cannot access system admin System Administrator Full platform — content, users, analytics Restricted to 2FA-enabled accounts only Session &amp; Auth Spec Auth provider: Clerk or Auth.js — Google OAuth (primary), Email+Password (secondary) JWT access token: 15-minute expiry Refresh token: 30-day expiry, httpOnly cookie, SameSite=Strict System Admin accounts: mandatory 2FA (TOTP) Rate limiting: 5 failed auth attempts per 15 minutes per IP Session invalidation on password change or subscription downgrade API-level enforcement of all tier and role restrictions — UI cannot bypass B5 — OFFLINE &amp; PWA SPECIFICATION ⚠ Offline scope must be precisely defined. &apos;Robust offline&apos; without specifics leads to conflicting implementations. Offline Availability Feature Offline Behaviour Cached modules Fully available — content, formulas, worked examples, practice questions GeoGebra diagrams Available if pre-downloaded. Show static screenshot fallback otherwise. Audio narrations Available if pre-downloaded Assessment submission Queued locally, submitted on reconnect. Server validates on sync. Progress / score sync Background sync when connection restored. Server score is authoritative. Leaderboard NOT available offline — show last cached snapshot with &apos;offline&apos; label New module unlocks NOT available offline — require server validation New content (unpublished) NOT available offline — requires fresh fetch Cache Strategy Asset Type Strategy App shell (HTML, JS, CSS) Cache First — long-lived, version-busted on deploy MathJax pre-rendered MathML Cache First — stored in MongoDB, served via CDN Module content JSON User-initiated download — not auto-downloaded (storage constraint) GeoGebra diagrams User-initiated download per topic Audio narrations User-initiated download — Pro only API responses (user progress) Network First, fallback to cache Leaderboard API Network Only — stale data is misleading Sync Conflict Resolution Server score is always authoritative Local score submitted only if server has no record for that session ID Duplicate session IDs rejected server-side Offline queue maximum: 50 pending submissions (prevent unbounded local storage) PWA Manifest Requirements manifest.json: icons at 192px and 512px, theme_color matching dark mode Add-to-homescreen: prompt after 3rd visit, not on first load Push notifications: opt-in only, used for streak warnings and module unlocks Background sync: Workbox BackgroundSyncPlugin for assessment submission queue B6 — MATH RENDERING &amp; INTERACTIVE DIAGRAMS MathJax Configuration Version: MathJax v3 minimum (v4 preferred when stable) Output: MathML primary (accessibility), SVG fallback for older browsers Pre-render all formulas server-side on Node.js — equations must be available offline Store pre-rendered MathML in MongoDB content documents — no client-side render required for known formulas Enable MathJax accessibility extensions: speech-rule-engine for screen reader equation reading Render target: &lt; 50ms per equation (pre-rendered), &lt; 200ms (client fallback) GeoGebra Integration Embed via GeoGebra API — not iFrame for production (iFrame has offline limitations) All GeoGebra applets: lazy-loaded, never block initial page render Labels in all GeoGebra diagrams: pulled from i18n translation keys, not hardcoded Mathematical logic in GeoGebra: language-invariant — only labels change Pre-download applets for offline: serialize GeoGebra state as JSON, restore offline Static screenshot fallback: auto-generated for offline display when applet not downloaded Example interactive uses: Taylor series slider, 3D rotation surfaces, unit circle animation, vector field explorer B7 — PERFORMANCE TARGETS 📌 All targets measured on mid-range Android device on 4G mobile network. This is the primary hardware profile for the Indian market. Metric Target First Contentful Paint (FCP) &lt; 1.5s on 4G mobile Time to Interactive (TTI) &lt; 3.5s on 4G mobile MathJax equation render (pre-rendered) &lt; 50ms MathJax equation render (client fallback) &lt; 200ms GeoGebra applet load &lt; 2.5s (lazy, non-blocking) Offline module access (from service worker) &lt; 300ms Search / filter response &lt; 200ms (Redis cache) GraphQL API p95 response &lt; 400ms WebSocket leaderboard update &lt; 500ms latency Assessment submission (online) &lt; 1s server acknowledgement Assessment submission (offline queue sync) &lt; 5s on reconnect Lighthouse mobile score &gt; 90 Lighthouse desktop score &gt; 95 Bundle size (initial JS) &lt; 200KB gzipped B8 — SECURITY &amp; COMPLIANCE Security Essentials Django built-in: SQL injection prevention, XSS protection, CSRF tokens on all forms Input sanitization: all user text sanitized before DB write — especially formula input fields Rate limiting: auth (5/15min), API (200 req/min per user), assessment submission (1 per session) HTTPS enforced sitewide — HSTS headers, no HTTP fallback API keys: never hardcoded — use environment variables, rotate quarterly System Admin: 2FA mandatory, audit log on all admin actions Assessment anti-cheat: server validates answer against question bank — client answer alone not trusted Compliance Requirements Regulation Requirement Markets GDPR Right to deletion, data residency option, cookie consent for EU traffic EU, Japan, Korea PDPB (India) Data localisation, consent, grievance officer for Indian users All Indian locales COPPA (US) No data collection from under-13 without parental consent Global (international students) WCAG 2.1 AA Accessibility compliance — screen readers, keyboard nav, contrast Global B9 — ANALYTICS &amp; MONITORING The One Metric That Predicts Retention 📌 Did the student complete at least 2 modules in their first session? If yes — they return. Track this above all else in Month 1. Product Analytics (PostHog — self-hostable) Module completion rates — identify which modules have high drop-off Average attempts to pass per module — flag modules needing question quality review Expertise reversal trigger firing rate — is the 80% threshold appropriate? Language distribution — which locales are most active Offline usage rate — what % of sessions have offline activity Leaderboard engagement — do students who view leaderboard have higher retention Conversion funnel: Guest → Free → Pro → Institutional Business Metrics Dashboard MRR, ARR, churn rate per tier CAC by acquisition channel vs LTV per tier Seat utilization for institutional accounts Content coverage: % of modules with all 9 language translations complete Infrastructure Monitoring Sentry: JS errors (frontend), Python exceptions (Django), Node.js errors Better Uptime: health checks on all services with PagerDuty alert Redis: cache hit rate target &gt; 85% for module content WebSocket: active connection count, message latency per region Celery: queue depth, task failure rate — alert if &gt; 5% failure on streak decay jobs B10 — TESTING STRATEGY Test Coverage Requirements Test Type Coverage Target &amp; Scope Unit tests (pytest + Vitest) All deterministic scoring, prerequisite enforcement, expertise reversal trigger logic Integration tests Auth flows, Stripe webhooks, prerequisite unlocks, score sync on reconnect E2E tests (Playwright) Full user journeys: registration, module completion, payment, certificate download i18n regression tests Formula rendering unchanged across all 9 locales after any content update Accessibility (axe-core) Zero critical violations on every PR — automated in CI Math accuracy review Human QA: every worked example reviewed by subject-matter expert before publish Cross-browser Chrome, Firefox, Safari (MathJax SVG has Safari rendering quirks) Mobile device testing iOS Safari + Chrome Android — real devices, not emulators only Load testing (k6) 10,000 concurrent WebSocket connections — leaderboard stress test Offline testing Simulate network drop during assessment — verify queue and sync behaviour Localization overflow Automated test for text overflow in all 9 languages on all screen sizes B11 — BUILD SEQUENCE (PHASED) 📌 Build only what matters, in the right order. Each phase must be fully tested before moving to the next. Phase 1 — Core (Weeks 1–4) Module schema + MongoDB content store 20 launch modules in English — full CLT compliance Next.js frontend: module reader with MathJax pre-rendering GeoGebra embeds for Level 1 and Level 2 modules (5 interactive diagrams) Django: user auth, module progress, scoring, prerequisite enforcement PostgreSQL schema fully deployed with migrations PWA: app shell caching, service worker base English + Tamil + Hindi translations for all 20 modules Phase 2 — Engagement (Weeks 5–8) Active recall assessment engine — full question randomization + anti-cheat Gamification: points, badges, streak system Node.js WebSocket leaderboard (global weekly) Expertise reversal trigger (80% threshold) — unit tested thoroughly Offline download: user-initiated module caching with background sync Audio narrations for English, Tamil, Hindi Stripe integration: Pro subscription with 14-day trial Phase 3 — Scale (Weeks 9–12) Remaining 4 Indian languages (Marathi, Kannada, Telugu, Malayalam) Certificate generation and shareable image cards Institutional tier: class dashboard, per-seat licensing Admin dashboard: content management, analytics, moderation Redis caching tuning: target &gt; 85% cache hit rate Load testing and performance optimization against defined targets Phase 4 — International (Month 4+) Japanese and Korean translations Korean and Japanese number formatting edge cases Expand GeoGebra interactive library to 30+ diagrams React Native app (iOS priority — shares 70% of web codebase) GDPR + PDPB compliance audit before international push B12 — PRE-LAUNCH CHECKLIST Content 20 modules written, technically reviewed, CLT-compliant, published English + Tamil + Hindi translations complete and QA&apos;d All formulas pre-rendered server-side — accessible offline 5 GeoGebra interactive diagrams working with localized labels Question bank: minimum 30 questions per module Technical MathJax renders correctly on iOS Safari and Chrome Android Expertise reversal trigger unit tested: 80% threshold fires correctly Prerequisite enforcement tested: API blocks access, not just UI Offline: assessment queue and sync verified with real network drop simulation All pages score &gt; 90 Lighthouse mobile Stripe payment flow tested end-to-end in test mode 2FA enforced and tested for all System Administrator accounts Sentry and PostHog active and firing in production Legal &amp; Compliance Privacy Policy: covers GDPR, PDPB, COPPA — reviewed by counsel Terms of Service published Cookie consent banner for EU/international visitors WCAG 2.1 AA: zero critical axe-core violations on all pages Business Stripe account activated and verified for INR + USD billing Uptime monitoring live with alerts to on-call Launch posts drafted: Reddit r/learnmath, r/india, Product Hunt, HN First 20 institutional prospects (schools/colleges) contacted with free pilot offer Teacher free access programme: 50 teachers — each brings a class PART A ADDENDUM — USER LIFECYCLE, BILLING &amp; NOTIFICATIONS A9 — USER LIFECYCLE MANAGEMENT 📌 This section covers every state a user account passes through: creation, verification, profile management, tier changes, and deletion. All flows must be implemented at the API level — UI cannot shortcut or bypass any step. A9.1 — Registration Flow Step Specification 1 — Input Email + password OR Google OAuth. No other methods at launch. 2 — Age gate Date of birth required. Users under 13: blocked with message to get parental account. Store DOB as year+month only (not full date) for privacy. 3 — Email verification Send verification email immediately on registration. Account created in &apos;pending_verification&apos; status. Unverified accounts: can browse free content only. Cannot save progress, take assessments, or subscribe. 4 — Verification email Token valid for 24 hours. Resend available after 2 minutes. After 3 resend attempts: 1-hour cooldown. 5 — Verified Account moves to &apos;active&apos; status. Free tier enabled. Guest progress (localStorage) migrated to database automatically. 6 — Welcome email Sent on first verified login: language preference prompt + 3 suggested starter modules. A9.2 — Age Verification &amp; Parental Consent (COPPA / GDPR) Under-13 detection: if DOB input yields age &lt; 13, block registration with friendly message Parental account flow (Phase 2): parent registers, creates child sub-account, provides consent Child accounts: no leaderboard participation, no data used for any analytics, no email marketing Age re-verification: if user later claims they were older, require ID verification via third-party service (Phase 2) Store minimum DOB data: year + month only, never full birthdate A9.3 — Profile Management Field Edit Rules Display name Editable anytime. Profanity filter applied. Min 2 chars, max 30 chars. Avatar Upload image (max 2MB, JPG/PNG/WebP). Resized to 128x128px server-side. Stored in Cloudflare R2. Email address Change requires: current password + verification email to new address. Old address notified of change. Password Change requires current password. New password: min 8 chars, 1 uppercase, 1 number. All active sessions invalidated on change. Language preference Changeable anytime. Content immediately re-served in new language. Formula rendering unchanged. Notification preferences Granular: streak warnings (push/email/none), module unlocks (push/none), weekly digest (email/none), marketing (email/none). Timezone Auto-detected on registration. Editable. Used for streak day boundary calculation and notification timing. A9.4 — Password Reset Flow User clicks &apos;Forgot password&apos; on login screen Enters registered email address System sends reset email if account exists (always show success message — never reveal if email is registered) Reset token: valid 1 hour, single-use, invalidated on use or expiry New password set: all active sessions across all devices invalidated immediately Confirmation email sent to address: &apos;Your password was changed. If this wasn&apos;t you, contact support.&apos; Rate limit: max 3 reset requests per email per hour A9.5 — Device &amp; Session Management Rule Specification Concurrent devices — Free Max 2 simultaneous active sessions Concurrent devices — Pro Max 5 simultaneous active sessions Concurrent devices — Institutional Unlimited (managed by institution) Session listing User can view: device type, browser, location (city/country), last active time for all active sessions Session revocation User can revoke any individual session or &apos;sign out all other devices&apos; Admin forced logout System admin can invalidate all sessions for a specific user (required for ban/suspension) New device login alert Email sent when login detected from new device/location. User can mark as &apos;not me&apos; to trigger immediate full session invalidation. A9.6 — Account Suspension &amp; Banning State Behaviour Warning Admin flags account. User sees warning banner on login. No access restriction yet. Suspended (temporary) Cannot log in. Subscription paused (not cancelled). Duration: 1–30 days. User emailed with reason and end date. Banned (permanent) Cannot log in or create new account with same email. Subscription cancelled, prorated refund issued. All sessions invalidated. Appeal Suspended/banned users can submit appeal via support form. No in-app flow needed at launch. A9.7 — Account Deletion (GDPR / PDPB Right to Erasure) ⚠ Account deletion must be fully implemented before launch. GDPR Article 17 and PDPB require this. Failure is a legal liability. User-initiated: Settings &gt; Account &gt; Delete Account. Require password confirmation + explicit checkbox &apos;I understand this is permanent&apos;. Grace period: 30-day soft-delete before hard delete. User can reactivate within 30 days by logging in. On soft delete: subscription cancelled immediately (no further charges). Access to content revoked. Leaderboard entries anonymised. On hard delete (day 30): all PII deleted — name, email, avatar, DOB. What is retained (anonymised): assessment scores (for question difficulty calibration), gamification ledger totals (for leaderboard historical integrity — user_id replaced with anonymous_id). What is deleted: profile, email, name, avatar, notification preferences, auth tokens, device sessions. Institutional learners: institutional admin must approve deletion if within active seat license period. GDPR data export: user can request full data export (JSON) before deletion. Delivered via email link within 72 hours. Deletion confirmation email: sent to address being deleted. Final email from the system. A10 — BILLING &amp; PAYMENTS (COMPLETE SPEC) ⚠ Every Stripe event must have a defined handler. Unhandled webhooks = subscription state drift = user access bugs. This section is non-negotiable before going live. A10.1 — Stripe Integration Architecture Payment processor: Stripe (primary). No alternative at launch. Currencies: INR (India), USD (international), JPY (Japan), KRW (Korea). Prices stored in Stripe per currency. Tax handling: Stripe Tax enabled for automatic GST (India 18%), consumption tax (Japan 10%), VAT (EU), and other regional taxes. Never calculate tax manually. Stripe Customer created on first subscription attempt — not on registration. Stripe Customer ID stored in subscriptions table alongside user_id. All billing logic executes server-side (Django). Client never touches Stripe directly except via Stripe.js for card input. Webhook endpoint: /api/webhooks/stripe — signed with Stripe webhook secret, verified on every request. A10.2 — Subscription Flows Free → Pro Upgrade User selects Pro plan on pricing page If in 14-day trial: no charge yet — trial clock starts if not already running If not in trial: Stripe Checkout or embedded payment form (Stripe Elements) On payment_intent.succeeded: update subscriptions table status=&apos;active&apos;, tier=&apos;pro&apos; Immediately: update user session JWT claims to include tier=&apos;pro&apos; Force token refresh on client: client re-fetches token, Pro content unlocks without page reload Send welcome-to-pro email within 60 seconds via Celery task Pro → Free Downgrade User cancels Pro subscription in Settings &gt; Billing Stripe subscription: set cancel_at_period_end=true (not immediate cancel) User retains Pro access until current period ends Show banner: &apos;Your Pro access ends on [date]. Upgrade again anytime.&apos; On customer.subscription.deleted webhook: set tier=&apos;free&apos; in DB, invalidate cached JWT Pro content in progress: modules remain visible but locked for further progress. Scores retained. Pro features gated: PDF export, certificates, offline unlimited — immediately removed after period end Send cancellation confirmation email + &apos;we&apos;ll miss you&apos; with reactivation link Trial Flow 14-day trial: starts on first Pro subscription creation, no credit card required Day 12: email — &apos;Your trial ends in 2 days. Add payment to continue.&apos; Day 13: push notification if opted in Day 14 (trial end): if no payment method — automatically downgrade to Free, send email Trial abuse prevention: one trial per verified email address. Device fingerprint check for repeat trial attempts from same device on new accounts. Trial reactivation: user who let trial expire can start fresh trial only once per 12 months A10.3 — Stripe Webhook Event Handlers ⚠ Every event below must have a handler. Log all unrecognised events. Alert on repeated handler failures. Stripe Event Required Handler Action payment_intent.succeeded Mark subscription active, unlock tier, send receipt email payment_intent.payment_failed Log failure, increment retry counter, send payment-failed email invoice.payment_succeeded Update subscription renewed_at date, send receipt invoice.payment_failed Start dunning sequence (see A10.4), do NOT revoke access yet invoice.upcoming Send 7-day renewal reminder email for annual plans customer.subscription.created Create/update subscriptions record, set tier customer.subscription.updated Sync plan, status, period_end to DB customer.subscription.deleted Set tier to free, revoke Pro access, invalidate sessions customer.subscription.trial_will_end Send trial-ending email (3 days before) charge.dispute.created Alert admin immediately, freeze account pending review charge.refunded Update refunds table, send refund confirmation to user A10.4 — Failed Payment &amp; Dunning Sequence Day Action Access Status Day 0 Payment fails. invoice.payment_failed received. Email: &apos;Payment failed — please update your card.&apos; FULL ACCESS — grace period Day 3 Stripe auto-retry. If fails: email reminder with update-card link. FULL ACCESS Day 7 Stripe auto-retry. If fails: email with urgency — &apos;Access suspends in 3 days&apos;. FULL ACCESS Day 10 Stripe auto-retry. If fails: access suspended. Email: &apos;Pro access paused. Update payment to restore.&apos; SUSPENDED Day 20 Final email: &apos;Your subscription will be cancelled in 10 days unless payment is resolved.&apos; SUSPENDED Day 30 Subscription cancelled. customer.subscription.deleted fires. Tier set to Free permanently. DOWNGRADED A10.5 — Refund Policy Scenario Policy Monthly plan — within 48 hours of charge Full refund, no questions asked Monthly plan — after 48 hours No refund. Access continues until period end. Annual plan — within 14 days Full refund if fewer than 5 modules completed Annual plan — after 14 days Prorated refund for unused months, minimum 2 months charged Institutional plan Negotiated per contract. Default: no refund after 30 days. Charge dispute (chargeback) Contest dispute with Stripe evidence. Freeze account pending outcome. Technical failure (our fault) Full refund regardless of timing — no exceptions A10.6 — Institutional Billing Billing cycle: annual only. Monthly not offered for institutional tier. Invoicing: Stripe generates PDF invoice automatically. Sent to billing_email on institutional account (separate from admin_email). Purchase order support: institutions can submit PO number — stored and printed on invoice. Seat over-limit: when used_seats reaches 90% of purchased seats, alert institutional admin via email. At 100%: new student assignments blocked until seats purchased. No auto-charging. Seat changes mid-cycle: adding seats prorated to remaining days. Removing seats: credit applied to next renewal. Bulk student import: CSV upload with columns: email, display_name, cohort. Max 1000 rows per upload. Validation errors reported per row. Student removal: when student removed from institution, their progress retained in personal account. Seat freed immediately. Contract expiry: 30-day advance notice email. If not renewed: all institutional learners downgraded to Free. Data retained 90 days before deletion. A10.7 — Coupons &amp; Discount Codes Coupon types: percentage discount, fixed amount off, free months Use cases: student verification discount (e.g., 50% off with .edu email), launch promotion, institutional pilot, influencer codes Redemption: entered at checkout. Validated server-side against Stripe coupon objects. Limits: single-use codes, per-user-once, or unlimited. Set in Stripe coupon config. Student email discount: auto-apply 30% discount for verified .edu or .ac.in email addresses Stacking: coupons do not stack with trial. Coupon applied after trial ends. A11 — EMAIL &amp; NOTIFICATIONS A11.1 — Email Service Provider: Resend (primary) — developer-friendly, reliable deliverability, React Email templates Fallback: Amazon SES if Resend unavailable All transactional emails: sent via Celery async tasks — never blocking the request cycle From address: noreply@mathpath.app for transactional, hello@mathpath.app for digest/marketing Unsubscribe: one-click unsubscribe link required on ALL non-transactional emails (CAN-SPAM + GDPR) Bounce handling: soft bounces — retry 3x then pause. Hard bounces — mark email invalid, block further sends, notify user on next login. Spam complaints: automatic unsubscribe from all marketing on spam report A11.2 — Transactional Email Templates (All Required at Launch) Template Trigger &amp; Content email_verification On registration. Subject: &apos;Confirm your MathPath email&apos;. Contains verification link (24hr expiry). welcome On first verified login. Subject: &apos;Welcome to MathPath&apos;. Language preference prompt + 3 starter modules. password_reset On reset request. Subject: &apos;Reset your MathPath password&apos;. Contains reset link (1hr expiry). password_changed On successful password change. Subject: &apos;Your password was changed&apos;. Security notice with support link. new_device_login On login from new device. Subject: &apos;New sign-in to your account&apos;. Device details + &apos;Not you?&apos; link. email_changed To old AND new email on email change. Old: &apos;Your email is being changed&apos;. New: &apos;Confirm your new email&apos;. trial_ending_3day 3 days before trial expiry. Subject: &apos;Your free trial ends in 3 days&apos;. Add payment CTA. trial_ending_1day 1 day before trial expiry. Subject: &apos;Last day of your free trial&apos;. Urgency + CTA. trial_expired On trial end with no payment. Subject: &apos;Your trial has ended&apos;. Downgrade notice + reactivate CTA. subscription_confirmed On successful subscription. Subject: &apos;You&apos;re now on Pro&apos;. Receipt + what&apos;s unlocked. payment_receipt On every successful charge. Subject: &apos;Your MathPath receipt&apos;. Amount, date, plan, invoice link. payment_failed On payment failure. Subject: &apos;Action needed: payment failed&apos;. Update card CTA. subscription_cancelled On cancellation. Subject: &apos;Your Pro subscription has been cancelled&apos;. Access end date + reactivate link. refund_issued On refund. Subject: &apos;Your refund is on the way&apos;. Amount, timeline (5–10 business days). account_suspended On suspension. Subject: &apos;Your account has been suspended&apos;. Reason + appeal link. account_deletion_confirm On deletion initiation. Subject: &apos;Account deletion started — 30 days to cancel&apos;. Reactivation link. data_export_ready On GDPR export complete. Subject: &apos;Your data export is ready&apos;. Download link (valid 48hrs). certificate_awarded On topic mastery. Subject: &apos;You&apos;ve mastered [Topic]!&apos;. Certificate image + share links. module_unlocked On prerequisite completion. Subject: &apos;[Module name] is now unlocked&apos;. Direct link to module. A11.3 — Digest &amp; Marketing Emails Email Frequency &amp; Content Weekly progress digest Every Sunday. Modules completed, streak status, points earned, what&apos;s next. Opt-out in preferences. Streak recovery Sent morning after streak lost. &apos;Your streak ended — start a new one today&apos;. Opt-out in preferences. Re-engagement Sent after 14 days of inactivity. &apos;We miss you — here&apos;s where you left off&apos;. Opt-out automatically after 3 ignored re-engagement emails. Monthly newsletter Monthly. New modules, platform updates, math facts. Marketing consent required (separate opt-in from transactional). A11.4 — Push Notifications (PWA + Future Native) Notification Trigger &amp; Timing Streak warning 22:00 user local time if no activity that day. Message: &apos;Don&apos;t lose your streak! Study one module tonight.&apos; Streak lost Morning after streak lost. &apos;Your streak ended. Start fresh today.&apos; Module unlocked Immediately on prerequisite completion. &apos;New module unlocked: [name]&apos; Trial ending 3 days before + 1 day before trial expiry Certificate awarded Immediately on topic mastery. &apos;You&apos;ve mastered [Topic]! View your certificate.&apos; Weekly leaderboard result Sunday midnight. &apos;This week&apos;s leaderboard is out. See your rank.&apos; All push notifications: opt-in only. Separate opt-in prompts per notification type. Push service: Web Push API via Workbox for PWA. Firebase Cloud Messaging (FCM) for React Native (Phase 4). Notification preferences: all types individually toggleable in Settings &gt; Notifications. PART B ADDENDUM — SESSIONS, API, DATABASE, INSTITUTIONAL &amp; SECURITY B13 — SESSION MANAGEMENT (EXTENDED SPEC) 📌 The original B4 covers auth methods and token durations. This section covers all remaining session mechanics, device management, Redis structure, and the offline JWT problem. B13.1 — Token Architecture Token Specification Access token (JWT) 15-minute expiry. Contains: user_id, tier, role, lang_pref, session_id. Signed with RS256 (asymmetric). Public key exposed at /.well-known/jwks.json. Refresh token 30-day expiry. Opaque random string (32 bytes, hex-encoded). Stored in Redis with TTL. httpOnly cookie, SameSite=Strict, Secure flag. Token rotation On every refresh: old refresh token invalidated, new one issued. Redis key updated atomically. Prevents refresh token replay attacks. Refresh token family tracking If a previously-invalidated refresh token is used: entire token family invalidated, all sessions for that user terminated. Indicates token theft. CSRF protection Double-submit cookie pattern for all state-mutating requests. Not needed for JWT-in-header requests from mobile. B13.2 — Redis Session Store Structure Key pattern: session:{user_id}:{session_id} TTL: 30 days (matches refresh token) Value (JSON): { user_id: string, session_id: string (UUID v4), refresh_token: string (hashed — never store raw), device_type: &apos;web&apos; | &apos;ios&apos; | &apos;android&apos; | &apos;pwa&apos;, browser: string, ip_address: string (hashed for privacy), location: { city, country }, created_at: ISO timestamp, last_active: ISO timestamp, tier: &apos;free&apos; | &apos;pro&apos; | &apos;institutional&apos;, is_offline_capable: boolean } Secondary index: sessions_by_user:{user_id} → SET of session_ids Used for: listing all sessions, revoking all sessions for a user Updated atomically with session create/delete B13.3 — Offline JWT Expiry Problem ⚠ This is the most overlooked session issue for offline-first apps. A user goes offline at 9am with a valid JWT. JWT expires at 9:15am. User is still offline at 10am. Without a solution, they are silently logged out and lose offline access. Solution: extended offline token stored separately in service worker cache On successful online auth: issue standard 15-min JWT + an &apos;offline continuation token&apos; (8-hour expiry, signed differently, flagged as offline-only) Offline continuation token: only valid when navigator.onLine === false. Rejected by server if sent online. When online JWT expires while offline: service worker transparently switches to offline continuation token for any cached API calls On reconnection: full re-authentication forced. Offline continuation token invalidated. Fresh JWT issued. Offline continuation token scope: read-only access to cached content + queued assessment submission only. Cannot unlock modules, change tier, or access leaderboard. Assessment sessions started offline: tagged with offline_session=true. Server validates extra carefully on sync. B13.4 — Concurrent Session Enforcement Tier Max Active Sessions Free 2 devices Pro 5 devices Institutional Unlimited System Admin 1 device B13.5 — Session Events &amp; Audit Log All session events written to session_audit_log table: session_created, session_refreshed, session_revoked, session_expired, token_theft_detected Retention: 90 days for standard users, 1 year for institutional and admin accounts Token theft events: immediately escalated to admin queue + user email alert Admin can query full session history for any user (for support and security investigations) B14 — API DESIGN SPECIFICATION B14.1 — REST vs GraphQL Split Service Protocol Auth (login, logout, refresh, reset) REST (Django) Webhooks (Stripe, push) REST (Django) Module content fetching GraphQL User progress &amp; scores GraphQL Leaderboard WebSocket (Node.js) Admin dashboard data GraphQL File upload (avatar, CSV import) REST (multipart/form-data) B14.2 — GraphQL Schema (Core Types) type User { id: ID! displayName: String! tier: Tier! langPref: Language! enrolledTopics: [TopicEnrollment!]! streak: Streak points: Int! badges: [Badge!]! } type Module { id: ID! title: String! # localized topic: Topic! difficulty: Int! prerequisites: [Module!]! isUnlocked(userId: ID!): Boolean! userProgress(userId: ID!): ModuleProgress } type ModuleProgress { status: ProgressStatus! # locked | unlocked | in_progress | completed lastScore: Float attempts: Int! workedExampleMode: ExampleMode! # full | partial | none } type Query { me: User module(id: ID!, lang: Language!): Module topicProgress(topicId: ID!): TopicProgress leaderboard(scope: LeaderboardScope!, weekOf: Date): [LeaderboardEntry!]! } type Mutation { submitAssessment(sessionId: ID!, answers: [Answer!]!): AssessmentResult! bookmarkModule(moduleId: ID!): Boolean! updateProfile(input: ProfileInput!): User! downloadModule(moduleId: ID!): DownloadToken! } B14.3 — API Security Rules GraphQL depth limiting: max query depth = 6. Reject deeper queries with 400 error. Prevents recursive query attacks. GraphQL complexity limiting: max complexity score = 100 per query. Each field has a cost weight. GraphQL introspection: disabled in production. Enabled in development only. Query whitelisting (Phase 2): only pre-approved query hashes accepted in production. Prevents ad-hoc API abuse. Pagination: all list queries use cursor-based pagination. Max page size: 50 items. No offset pagination (inconsistent at scale). Authentication: Bearer token in Authorization header for REST. Same token passed as X-Auth-Token header for GraphQL (not cookie — mobile clients can&apos;t set cookies on GraphQL easily). API versioning: URL-based for REST (/api/v1/). GraphQL: schema evolution with deprecation warnings, no versioning. B14.4 — GraphQL Rate Limiting Client Type Rate Limit Unauthenticated 30 requests / minute Free tier user 120 requests / minute Pro tier user 300 requests / minute Institutional admin 600 requests / minute System admin Unlimited Webhook endpoints 500 requests / minute per IP B15 — DATABASE EXTENDED SPEC B15.1 — PostgreSQL Indexing Strategy ⚠ Missing indexes are the most common cause of performance degradation at scale. Define them now, not after launch. -- High-frequency lookup indexes CREATE INDEX idx_module_progress_user ON module_progress(user_id); CREATE INDEX idx_module_progress_module ON module_progress(module_id); CREATE INDEX idx_module_progress_user_module ON module_progress(user_id, module_id); CREATE INDEX idx_assessment_sessions_user ON assessment_sessions(user_id); CREATE INDEX idx_gamification_user ON gamification_ledger(user_id); CREATE INDEX idx_badges_user ON badges(user_id); CREATE INDEX idx_leaderboard_week ON leaderboard_weekly(week_start, points DESC); CREATE INDEX idx_subscriptions_user ON subscriptions(user_id); CREATE INDEX idx_subscriptions_stripe ON subscriptions(stripe_id); CREATE INDEX idx_streaks_user ON streaks(user_id); -- Partial indexes for active records CREATE INDEX idx_active_subscriptions ON subscriptions(user_id) WHERE status = &apos;active&apos;; CREATE INDEX idx_pending_verification ON users(email) WHERE status = &apos;pending_verification&apos;; B15.2 — GDPR Deletion Cascade Table On User Delete users Hard delete after 30-day grace period subscriptions Cancel in Stripe first, then hard delete record topic_enrollments Hard delete module_progress Hard delete assessment_sessions Anonymise: set user_id = anonymous_id, nullify answers_json gamification_ledger Anonymise: replace user_id with anonymous_id, retain balance totals streaks Hard delete badges Hard delete leaderboard_weekly Replace display_name with &apos;Deleted User&apos;, retain score for integrity daily_active_recall Hard delete session_audit_log Anonymise: replace user_id with anonymous_id, retain event types notifications Hard delete B15.3 — Data Archival Policy Data Type Retention Assessment sessions (completed) 2 years active, then archive Gamification ledger events Permanent (anonymised after account delete) Session audit log 90 days (standard users) Session audit log (admin/institutional) 1 year Email send log 30 days Failed webhook events 7 days Soft-deleted accounts 30 days B15.4 — Connection Pooling &amp; Read Replicas Connection pooling: PgBouncer in transaction mode. Max 100 connections to PostgreSQL. Pool size: 20 per Django worker. Read replica: add at 10,000 DAU. Route all SELECT queries for leaderboard and analytics to replica. Read replica lag tolerance: leaderboard can tolerate 5-second lag. Module progress queries must hit primary. MongoDB: connection pool size 50 per service instance. Atlas handles replica set automatically. B15.5 — Content Versioning Rules Change Type Version Action Typo / formatting fix Increment patch: 1.0.0 → 1.0.1 Step explanation rewrite Increment minor: 1.0.0 → 1.1.0 Question answer changed Increment major: 1.0.0 → 2.0.0 Prerequisite structure changed Increment major + admin review Module retired status = &apos;deprecated&apos; Translation staleness: when English module version increments minor or major, all non-English translations flagged as &apos;needs_review&apos; in admin dashboard Student mid-module version change: if module version increments while student is in progress, show notice on next load: &apos;This module was updated. Your progress is preserved.&apos; B16 — INSTITUTIONAL FEATURES (EXTENDED SPEC) B16.1 — SSO &amp; Identity Federation Phase 3 feature. Required for large institutional deals. Protocol: SAML 2.0 (most common in schools/universities) + OIDC (for modern institutions using Azure AD / Google Workspace) Implementation: django-allauth with SAML plugin OR Okta/Auth0 as identity broker Per-institution SSO config: each institution gets its own IdP configuration. Managed by system admin. JIT (Just-In-Time) provisioning: new users auto-created on first SSO login if they have a valid institutional email domain SSO users: cannot change email or password (managed by institution&apos;s IdP). Can change display name, avatar, language preference. B16.2 — Class &amp; Cohort Management Feature Specification Create cohort Institutional admin creates named cohorts (e.g., &apos;Class 11A&apos;, &apos;Batch 2025&apos;). Assign topic curriculum to cohort. Assign students Add students individually by email, or bulk import via CSV (max 1000 rows). Students receive invite email. Module assignment Admin can assign specific modules with optional due dates. Due dates shown to students in their dashboard. Due date enforcement After due date: module still accessible, but marked &apos;overdue&apos; in admin view. Not locked — do not punish students. Class leaderboard Weekly leaderboard scoped to cohort only. Separate from global leaderboard. Cohort progress report Admin sees: per-student completion %, average score per module, time spent, modules not started. Export Export cohort progress as CSV. Available anytime, generated on-demand. Email delivery for large exports (&gt;500 students). B16.3 — LTI Integration (Phase 3) Standard: LTI 1.3 (not 1.1 — deprecated and insecure) Supported LMS: Canvas, Moodle, Blackboard, Google Classroom Launch flow: student clicks MathPath link in LMS → LTI launch → auto-login or account creation → land on assigned module Grade passback: on module completion, score sent back to LMS gradebook via LTI Advantage Scores service Deep linking: instructors can browse MathPath module library from within LMS and select specific modules to assign LTI config per institution: tool consumer key, shared secret, launch URL — managed by system admin B16.4 — Institutional Admin Dashboard Dashboard Section Contents Overview Active seats used/total, cohorts count, overall completion rate, avg score across institution this month Students Searchable list: name, email, cohort, last active, modules completed, current streak Cohorts Per-cohort: assigned modules, completion rate, average score, at-risk students (0 activity in 7+ days) Module performance Per-module: attempts, pass rate, avg score, avg time — identify hard modules At-risk students Auto-flagged: no activity in 7+ days, 3+ consecutive failed modules, &lt;40% completion of assigned work Reports Exportable: student progress CSV, cohort summary PDF, module difficulty report Billing Seat usage, renewal date, invoice history, add seats button Settings SSO configuration, billing email, institution name/logo, sub-admin management B17 — SECURITY EXTENDED SPEC B17.1 — HTTP Security Headers ⚠ Security headers must be configured at the CDN/proxy layer (Cloudflare) AND at the application layer. Never rely on only one. Content-Security-Policy: default-src &apos;self&apos;; script-src &apos;self&apos; &apos;nonce-{random}&apos; https://cdn.geogebra.org; style-src &apos;self&apos; &apos;unsafe-inline&apos;; # MathJax requires this img-src &apos;self&apos; data: https://r2.mathpath.app; frame-src https://www.geogebra.org; connect-src &apos;self&apos; https://api.mathpath.app wss://rt.mathpath.app; font-src &apos;self&apos; https://cdn.mathpath.app; X-Frame-Options: DENY X-Content-Type-Options: nosniff Referrer-Policy: strict-origin-when-cross-origin Permissions-Policy: geolocation=(), microphone=(), camera=() Strict-Transport-Security: max-age=31536000; includeSubDomains; preload B17.2 — Subresource Integrity (SRI) All CDN-loaded assets (MathJax, GeoGebra) must have SRI hashes in HTML SRI hash generation: automated in build pipeline — never manually maintained On SRI failure: browser blocks asset load. Fallback: serve from own CDN with lower performance GeoGebra: hosted on their CDN — pin to specific version, monitor for changes B17.3 — Dependency Security GitHub Dependabot: enabled on all repositories. Auto-PRs for security patches. Snyk: integrated in CI/CD pipeline. Block deployment if critical vulnerabilities found. npm audit: run on every build. Zero high/critical vulnerabilities in production build. Python safety: run pip-audit on every Django build. Secret scanning: GitHub secret scanning enabled. Pre-commit hook to prevent accidental API key commits. B17.4 — Data Encryption In transit: TLS 1.2 minimum, TLS 1.3 preferred. HSTS preload enabled. At rest (PostgreSQL): AES-256 encryption via managed database provider (Supabase/RDS both offer this). At rest (MongoDB Atlas): encryption at rest enabled by default on Atlas. At rest (Redis): encryption at rest enabled on managed Redis provider. File storage (R2): server-side encryption enabled. Sensitive fields in DB: refresh tokens stored as bcrypt hash (not raw). Passwords: argon2id (not bcrypt — stronger against GPU attacks). PII field encryption: email addresses encrypted at column level in PostgreSQL using pgcrypto extension (searchable encryption). B17.5 — Penetration Testing Plan Phase Scope Timeline Pre-launch Authentication flows, session management, payment flows, API endpoints, RBAC bypass attempts 2 weeks before launch Post-launch (6 months) Full application pentest including new features, institutional SSO, LTI integration Month 7 Annual Full scope recurring test Annually thereafter Provider: specialist AppSec firm — not automated scanner only Scope includes: OWASP Top 10, API security (OWASP API Top 10), business logic vulnerabilities Responsible disclosure: publish security policy at /security.txt and security@mathpath.app Bug bounty programme (Phase 2): Hackerone or Bugcrowd platform, $50–$5000 reward tiers B18 — MOBILE &amp; FORM FACTOR SPECIFICATION B18.1 — Responsive Breakpoints Breakpoint Screen Width Layout xs &lt; 480px (phone portrait) 1-column. Bottom navigation bar. GeoGebra full-width. Steps stacked. sm 480–767px (phone landscape) 1-column, compact header. GeoGebra capped at 50vh. md 768–1023px (tablet portrait) 2-column: collapsible sidebar + content. GeoGebra inline. lg 1024–1279px (tablet landscape / small laptop) 2-column: persistent sidebar 280px + content. xl 1280px+ (desktop) 3-column: sidebar 280px + content + context panel 300px. B18.2 — Mobile UX Rules Minimum tap target: 44×44px on all interactive elements (WCAG 2.5.5) Formula input on mobile: custom keyboard overlay with common math symbols (∫, √, π, θ, Σ) + numpad Long-press equation: copy raw LaTeX to clipboard GeoGebra on phone: simplified controls — sliders large enough for touch. Pan/zoom via pinch. Landscape mode: detected via matchMedia. GeoGebra switches to landscape layout automatically. Keyboard avoidance: when soft keyboard opens, content scrolls up to keep active input visible. Never hide behind keyboard. Bottom navigation bar (mobile only): Topics | Progress | Leaderboard | Profile Swipe gestures: swipe right on module = go back to topic list. No accidental swipe-back during assessment. B18.3 — Tablet Layout iPad / Android tablet (768px+): two-column layout is primary. Sidebar persistent, not hamburger. GeoGebra on tablet: full interactive controls. Apple Pencil on iPad: works naturally with GeoGebra drag interactions. Split-view multitasking (iPad): app functions correctly at 50% screen width (minimum viable width: 375px). B18.4 — React Native Spec (Phase 4) Area Specification Codebase sharing 70% shared logic via React Native Web. Platform-specific: navigation, push notifications, offline storage. iOS priority Ship iOS first — target STEM students who skew iPhone in India/Japan/Korea. Offline storage React Native MMKV (faster than AsyncStorage) for cached module content. Math rendering MathJax React Native wrapper OR KaTeX-native package. Benchmark both before choosing. GeoGebra GeoGebra native SDK if available, else WebView with communication bridge. Push notifications Firebase Cloud Messaging (FCM) for both iOS and Android. Deep linking Universal links (iOS) + App Links (Android) for certificate sharing and module direct links. App Store requirements In-app purchase via Apple IAP (mandatory for iOS) — Stripe for web, IAP for native. Account for 30% Apple fee in iOS pricing. B19 — UPDATED PRE-LAUNCH CHECKLIST (COMPLETE) 📌 This replaces and extends B12. All items must be checked before go-live. User Lifecycle Registration flow: age gate, email verification, guest migration — all tested E2E Password reset: self-service flow tested, rate limiting verified Profile editing: all fields editable, avatar upload working, email change verified Account deletion: 30-day soft delete, hard delete cascade, GDPR export — all tested Device session listing and revocation working for Free and Pro tier limits Offline JWT continuation token: tested with network drop simulation Billing &amp; Payments All 12 Stripe webhook handlers implemented and tested in Stripe webhook test mode Upgrade, downgrade, and cancellation flows tested end-to-end Trial flow: day 12/13/14 emails triggered correctly in test mode Failed payment dunning sequence: all 5 stages tested Stripe Tax enabled and verified for INR + USD Refund flow: both manual admin refund and automated tested Institutional billing: bulk import, seat management, invoice generation tested Email &amp; Notifications All 18 transactional email templates: rendered and tested in all 3 Phase 1 languages Unsubscribe links working on all non-transactional emails Push notification opt-in flow working on PWA Email bounces: invalid email handling tested Celery task queue: email delivery confirmed in staging under load Security CSP headers verified — no console errors from GeoGebra or MathJax CSP violations SRI hashes in place for all CDN assets 2FA enforced for all System Administrator accounts Argon2id password hashing confirmed in Django settings PostgreSQL encryption at rest verified on managed provider Dependabot enabled, zero critical vulnerabilities in final build Pre-launch penetration test completed and critical findings resolved Mobile &amp; PWA All breakpoints tested: xs through xl on real devices 44px tap targets verified on all interactive elements Mobile formula keyboard overlay working Offline mode tested: module access, assessment queue, sync on reconnect PWA installable on iOS Safari and Chrome Android Push notification opt-in and delivery tested on PWA No AI. No shortcuts. Just deterministic, honest education. Build it right. Build it for everyone.
